in our first session we took a brief
overview of the first man who is usually
considered to be the father of ancient
Greek philosophy namely thales and we
saw that thales had his quest for the RK
or the Ultimate Reality that would
explain everything else
and he found that in water now between
the work of thales in the 6th Century BC
and the appearance of Socrates a while
later there were there was a series of
significant
pre-socratic philosophers and we're not
going to have time in this brief
overview to look at each one of them in
detail
but there was a progression of thinkers
who built upon the preliminary work of
those who went before them and and they
had some strange names for example we
meet a man by the name of anax amenities
and another one whose name is very
similar and acts amander
and we run into people like impedicles
and ethanagarus and Democritus and
there's a whole series of these people
and they
debated among themselves what was
Ultimate Reality and acts amenities for
example
challenged the thesis of thales that
Ultimate Reality was water
and he substituted for the concept of
water the idea of air
he thought that that was a superior
substance to explain Ultimate Reality
from water now remember how we looked at
thales and we saw the thales was
interested in questions of being
questions of Life questions of motion
and anaxomenes came on and said well if
water can account for these things what
about air
because air is something that every
living thing needs in order to survive
and if we think that water has the
ability to propel itself that is this
hilozoicistic it can move on its own
initiative what about the wind
what about the air currents that seem to
be able to come up and move without
anything pushing them or pooling them
and he said
air
like water has the ability to be
involved in condensation or rare faction
you condense air
and you will get
forms of moisture and things of that
sort and out of rare faction rarified
air you get gases you get fire you get
things of that sort and so he argued
against anax amenities excuse me against
thales that the ultimate substance was
air now other philosophers came along
and said well it's not water or air it's
Earth it's the substance of of the
ground
or another one would come along and say
no
fire and we'll look more at fire later
on
and still another one would come along
and say no it's not any of those four
things but it's really all four of them
together that there are four basic
elements
Beyond which you can't reduce things
that all things are made up of either
earth air
far or water
now you've heard that you've heard of
the four basic elements of reality
according to the ancient world earth air
fire and water
but no sooner does that theory come to
Center Stage then somebody pops up and
said no wait a minute if there are four
basic elements from which everything
comes
and the the Ultimate Reality is not
singular but plural
doesn't that leave us with the many
and not the one
it leaves us with diversity
without Unity
so there's got to be something behind
these four elements of earth air fire
and water
that gives purpose and Order and Harmony
and unity to those four primary elements
and so now the quest was on for what
they called the fifth
essence
now we might say that this was the
quintessential philosophical inquiry
you've heard that word haven't you
quintus quintessence or quintessential
what does it mean literally
Quint means five
five or the fifth essence
that which is above and beyond the four
basic elements that which explains
all of the four basic elements is called
that which is not just essential but
quintessential and so we get the word
from that well in this whole process
anaximander comes up with an idea
that from the perspective of history
was extremely important
he said that Ultimate Reality really
Ultimate Reality
is what he called
I'll transliterate it the appearing
or the operon
from the from the Greek language
you've probably never heard of that word
in your life and that's okay
but what he meant by this little word am
I wrong
was that
which is boundless
and
ageless
that which is boundless
and ageless
oh for something to be boundless means
that it doesn't have any
boundaries
there is no finite Dimension that can
capture it or contain it
in a word whatever is boundless must be
infinite
and whatever is Ageless
doesn't have a birthday
and has no birthday parties
because if it has no age it is somehow
above and beyond the normal currents of
time
so in a word that which is Ageless is
that which is eternal
now you and I
have an age
we all have birthdays we all have a
finite point of beginning in time
but we also have finite limits of space
as creatures we have natural boundaries
I'm experiencing that now not in an
abstract
philosophical way but in a concrete
existential way as we are videotaping
this program
you see because behind the scenes behind
the cameras and the microphones we have
directors and they wave their hands at
me and tell me how much time I have but
the worst thing they do is that they put
these things on the floor that I don't
think maybe you can see right now
through the camera but there are pieces
there's a piece of black tape right
there and then over here there's more
black tape and that black black types
goes over here and then there's another
one along here
they've put me in a cage they're saying
I like to walk around I'm a parapathetic
teacher and when I'm moving
it's hard for the cameramen to keep me
in focus and in sight so they put me in
this cage
they bound me say I am not infinite but
now I wish I were then I try to trick
them I come right up to the edge of
these tapes and I lean and see see what
happens well in the meantime I'll be
satisfied with my creatureliness and try
to stay within the boundary
but nobody's going to mistake me for
Ultimate Reality
or the Supreme metaphysical point of
unity
for the entire
realm of existence
no
and maximander said
that which is Ultimate
can have no finite bounds
and that which is truly ultimate
cannot have a beginning in time
or a definite age to its lifespan
but it must be infinite
and eternal
let me just make one observation at this
point
what we're seeing in this quest for
Ultimate Reality of the ancient
pre-socratics
is really what we would call The Pursuit
Of God
and in Greek philosophy the idea of
monotheism
is a relatively late development
after all kinds of preliminary stages
have first been worked through
whereas to the Hebrew thinker
he starts
with the infinite and the Eternal his
wisdom literature begins with the words
n r k in the beginning
God
created the heavens and the earth that
is at the very beginning of his
literature he introduces the app Iran
the
boundless
eternal
infinite one who creates all things now
I also have to say at this point as we
will see further on
that even when the Greeks did come up
with the idea
of an infinite Eternal source of unity
that holds all things together
and brings purpose and Harmony out of
all things
for these thinkers at this time
the idea of the
Eternal infinite
is just that an abstract idea
what distinguishes that so sharply
from Biblical thought
as to the Jew for example of the Old
Testament
the one who is infinite and eternal
is
a one
who
that is it is a he
a personal living being
not simply an abstract power or Force
but rather has personality that's
radical
in ancient
theoretical thought
now in and among these other
pre-socratics such as anaximander and
the rest
the tension that emerged
was over different ways of understanding
The RK or the Ultimate Reality
and I'm going to try to to give you a
little chart here to make it easier to
understand
some of the thinkers as we've already
seen
believed that Ultimate Reality
was a single substance like air or water
or Fire or the quintessence whatever
and so we will say of those philosophers
that they were all monists
now a monist is one
who Embraces monism
and
monism teaches
that their that all reality
in the final analysis is one
it always leads to some form of
pantheism
monism says there really is only one
reality there is unity and all diversity
is simply an outward manifestation of
that underlying Unity
and that which is diverse does not have
the ultimate level of reality that the
single one many of the ancient
philosophers spoke about God by calling
him
law one
the one
because they were monists you know water
air one substance explains everything
and everything that is participates to
some degree in that single substance or
single being
that is the one
now other
philosophers at this time
were pluralists
and by that I mean that they believed
that we could not reduce reality to one
single substance or Essence
as we've already seen there were those
who said There are four basic elements
earth air Fire and Water they would be
the who those people would be pluralists
others expanded upon that and said no
it's not merely four elements
but a multitude of elements one
philosopher for example said the world
is made up
of an infinite variety of seeds now
where would they get an idea like that
well you see it from from your gardening
experience if you want to grow cucumbers
you have to grow them from cucumber
seeds not from rose seeds and if you
want a geranium or whatever they each
reality has its particular seed you
don't get elephants from Human seeds
and you don't get kangaroos from
elephant seeds that everything that is
alive
has its progeny through some seminal
process through the use of seeds
and so this fella said that there's an
infinite number of seeds in the world
from which everything is made
another one Democritus for example in
his somewhat crude view of reality
talked about
a multiplicity of particular bits of
reality that he called
atoms
maybe you've heard of the atomic theory
of the ancient philosopher Democritus
now it's not to be confused or equated
with contemporary atomic theory but
there have certain things there are
certain things in common between modern
Atomic physics and the ancient thought
of Democritus and that that which is
common is the idea that reality is made
up of these little units
because the term atom means Unity
and when we had an atomic bomb
we had a linguistic crisis all of a
sudden
because the word Adam
was thought to refer to that smallest
indivisible particle bit of which all of
reality is made but then one afternoon
boom somebody divided the atom and
things got a little bit shaky out there
but now we talk about
subatomic particles don't we but we
still have the idea that all forms of
reality are made up of some kind of
congregation or amalgamation of bits of
reality that we call atoms or seeds or
whatever
so anybody who believes that Ultimate
Reality is more than one I mean a lot of
philosophies Eastern philosophy believes
in dualism saying that all of reality
can be resolved or reduced to two equal
and opposite powers or forces but still
as long as there's more than one you're
in the pluralism
monism refers everything back to one
single substance pluralists can have two
or an infinite number of units of
reality
so the struggle in ancient philosophy
was in the first instance between monus
and pluralists
now the Alias for example was a monist
Democritus was a pluralist
but the plot thickens
other question that came up was what is
the nature of these units of reality
are these units of reality whether
singular or plural are they physical
or non-physical
thales for example said that everything
is water and water is a substance so
that we would think oh well then he is a
physical monist or what is called
a corporeal
monist
now let me back up and make it simple a
corporeal monist is somebody who
believes that everything that exists
is simply one form or another or
manifestation of a single physical
substance
matter
and nothing exists except matter
now there were also
incorporeal monus
who believe that Ultimate Reality is
single
but it's not physical
it's like an infinite
qualitative
spiritual power
that has no dimensions
has no weight doesn't take up any
specific amount of space
and we have to be careful here and you
know in a desire to simplify I always
run the risk of distorting
but when the ancient people were talking
about Spirit or incorporeal
many of them would include
things like air
or gas
and things that we would look at as
being physical just in a different form
of physical substance but for them
anything that wasn't solid was
considered incorporeal for many of them
at least so in any case you have a
debate between monus and pluralists and
then you have a debate between
corporealis and incorporealists so that
a person could be a monist who believed
that all of reality could be reduced to
one physical substance or they could say
that everything is the manifestation of
some
unphysical non-physical substance like
we might say energy
you think about energy you talk about
energy what is it
I asked that to a a physics Professor
once I said what is energy he says oh
that's easy he says it's the ability to
do work I said I'm not asking what it
can do I wonder what it is he says well
it's MC squared I said I want to know
it's mathematical equivalent I want to
know what it is because you people keep
talking about it as if it is as if there
really is something out there called
Energy
or is that just a word for unknown
concept X
and we don't usually think to that level
we say oh okay matter energy and go on
with that all right on the other hand
pluralists could also be
corporeal or incorporeal
some believe that all things can be
reduced to several physical things where
others said no it can be reduced to
several non-physical things
and so it's in this context that the
next chapter
of emerging Greek philosophy takes place
and we'll look at that in our next
session